<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to the Honourable Robert Boyle, Esq., defending the divine authority of the Holy Scripture and that it alone is the rule of faith in answer to Father Simon's Critical history of the Old Testament / written by C.M. Du Veil.</title>
            <author>Veil, Charles-Marie de, 1630-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64788</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V176</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6969</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11967309</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11967309</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51756</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64788)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51756)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 521:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to the Honourable Robert Boyle, Esq., defending the divine authority of the Holy Scripture and that it alone is the rule of faith in answer to Father Simon's Critical history of the Old Testament / written by C.M. Du Veil.</title>
                  <author>Veil, Charles-Marie de, 1630-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Malthus ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Simon, Richard, 1638-1712. --  Histoire critique du Vieux Testament.</term>
               <term>Bible --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Bible --  Evidences, authority, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51756:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER To the Honourable <hi>Robert Boyle, Eſq.</hi> DEFENDING The DIVINE AUTHORITY OF THE HOLY SCRIPTURE, And that it alone is the RULE of FAITH. IN ANSWER TO Father <hi>Simon</hi>'s Critical Hiſtory OF THE Old Teſtament.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>C. M. Du Veil,</hi> D D.</p>
            <q>Sufficit Chriſtiano ad confutandum errorem quemlibet dicere, <hi>Scriptura non habet.</hi> 
               <bibl>Lutherus.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>The Fathers in their Homilies did uſe conſtantly to declare to the People, what they were to believe, and what they were to practiſe out of the Scripture. <bibl>
                  <hi>Dean Tillotſon's</hi> Rule of Faith, <hi>P. 1. Sect. 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Malthus</hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:51756:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51756:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER To the Honourable <hi>Robert Boyle, Eſq.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>To prove that the Scripture alone is the Rule of Faith,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honourable Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>A Book indeed full of Learning, Printed at <hi>Paris</hi> without a Title-Sheet, came lately to my hands, intituled, <hi>The Critical Hiſtory of the Old Teſtament;</hi> Whereof Father <hi>Simon,</hi> Prieſt of the <hi>Oratory</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> is thought to be the Author. He pretends to prove in that Work, that nothing for certain can be aſſerted in Religion, unleſs Tradition be joyned with the Scripture for the Deciſion of Queſtions of Faith. <hi>There is without doubt Ignorance,</hi> ſays that Author in his Preface, <hi>or Prepoſſeſſion in the Minds</hi> of the Proteſtants, <hi>Who pretend that the Scripture is clear of it ſelf.</hi> Nevertheleſs Sir, nothing is more certain in all that can be called <hi>Tradition,</hi> than this Principle
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51756:3"/>of the Proteſtants. St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in his third Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> obſerves after <hi>Origen</hi> this difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Philoſophers and the Authors of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that the Philoſophers are obſcure, whereas the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Prophets being the common Maſters of the Univerſe, have written after ſo clear a manner, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Capacity may be inſtructed in their Doctrine by the reading alone thereof. And in the ſame <hi>Homily</hi> that Doctor maintains that the ignorance of the Sacred Scriptures is the ſource of the Corrupted Morals, as well as of all the Hereſies. St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> in the ſecond Book of the <hi>Christian Doctrine</hi> ſays, Chap. 9. <hi>In iis quae aperte in Scriptura poſita ſunt, inveniuntur illa omnia quae Continent fidem moreſque vivendi: In thoſe things which are plainly laid down in Scripture, are found all thoſe things which pertain to Faith, and the Rules of Living.</hi> This the Learned <hi>Gerſon,</hi> Chancellor of the Univerſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> expreſſes in theſe terms: <hi>Senſus Literalis Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae ſatis expreſſus eſt in iis quae ſunt neceſſaria ad Salutem.</hi> And this induced the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> to make this <hi>Canon</hi> with great reaſon, in the <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>London</hi> in 1552, and 1562.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Scripture containeth all things neceſſary to Salvation: So that whatſoever is not read therein, nor may be proved thereby, although it be ſome time received of the Faithful as godly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for an Order and Comelineſs, yet no man ought to be conſtrained to believe it as an Article of Faith, or reputed requiſite to the Neceſſity of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Father <hi>Simon</hi> does diſingeniouſly quote the thought of St. <hi>Augustin</hi> in the 7th. Chap. of the third book of his <hi>Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Hiſtory. That Holy Doctor ſuppoſes,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>that the Scripture is obſcure and hard to be underſtood, and yet he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51756:3"/>adds that for the moſt part what is obſcure in one place is found laid plainly open in another, and that what regards the belief and manners is much more clearly expreſſed in the Bible than all the rest.</hi> Now to read the thought of St. <hi>Augustin</hi> in the Book of Father <hi>Simon,</hi> that Doctor ſeems only to aſſert that commonly the Scripture is clear in what concerns the belief and manners, nay and more clear than in all the reſt. But St. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſays more in the Words Cited: for he ſays abſolutely that all we ought to believe and do, is found clearly in the Scripture, &amp; therefore according to Father <hi>Simon, There is without doubt either Ignorance or Prepoſſeſſion of Mind in St. Auguſtin,</hi> as well as in St. <hi>Chryſoſtom, Gerſon,</hi> &amp; general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in all the Great Divines of Antiquity, who have been perſwaded with
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>in Jerem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Origen,</hi> that not any Sentiment is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of Faith, unleſs it be proved by Scripture; nor any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of the ſame Scripture to be admitted, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it be confirmed and ſupported upon Paſſages of the Old or New Teſtament: for this Reaſon is it that in the Decree of <hi>Gratian,</hi> Diſtinct. 27. in the Chap. which begins with this word <hi>Relatum,</hi> there is an expreſs or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to decide all Controverſies by the Holy Writ, and to explain the obſcure paſſages which are met with therein by the Scriptures themſelves: <hi>ex ipſis Scripturis.</hi> But this is ſufficient Entertaining you Sir, with the groundleſs Sentiment of Father <hi>Simon,</hi> touching the inſufficiency of the Scripture, for the inſtructing Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Religion. Now I proceed to the three proofs which he makes uſe of for the Eſtabliſhing of his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <p>The firſt is taken from the great Changes which have happen'd as well in the Original Text as in the Verſions of the Scripture. This proof may ſeem to have ſome force upon an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> or a <hi>Pagan;</hi> but not upon a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:51756:4"/>Who knows, that notwithſtanding the Changes that have been made in Scripture, <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and the Fathers of the Church, have always proved the Truth of their Doctrine by the Scripture. As for what concerns the Fathers, I ſhall ſhow it am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply in my anſwer to the third proof of Father <hi>Simon,</hi> though what I have already urged might ſuffice. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles; Father <hi>Simon</hi> ſays, <hi>That they have fitted the Teſtimonys which they Cited out of the Old Teſtament, to the Explications received and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized by Tradition.</hi> But this is a falſe fore-judging of that Father, of whom with reaſon theſe Words of St. <hi>Jerome</hi> may be ſaid, <hi>Hoc de Scripturis Authoritatem non habet, ideo ea facilitate Contemnitur qua probatur; This has no Authority from Scriptures, therefore may be rejected with the ſame eaſe it is admitted.</hi> Jeſus repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends Traditions, and yet father <hi>Simon</hi> would make us believe that he eſtabliſhes his Doctrine by Tradition, and that he only makes uſe of the Word of God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Pre-judgment of Tradition. It was a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> founded upon a paſſage of the Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> miſunderſtood, that <hi>Elias</hi> was to precede by his Preaching the coming of the <hi>Meſſias;</hi> but the Goſpel tells us, that tradition did ill interpret the Prophet <hi>Malachy,</hi> who did not pretend to ſpeak of the Perſon of the Prophet <hi>Elias,</hi> but of <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> who was to forego <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, in Spiritu &amp; Virtute Eliae.</hi> It is evident by the 5th. Chapter, of St. <hi>Matth.</hi> that the <hi>Jews</hi> explaining the Scriptures by the Pre-judgment of Tradition, had very faulty Morals: But Jeſus Chriſt who came not to deſtroy the Law and the Prophets, but to fulfil them, rejects the falſe Expoſitions given to the Law by the <hi>Jews</hi> according to their Traditions, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers the real ſence thereof conformably to other paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51756:4"/>of the Old Teſtament, which contain in clear terms the ſame things, which <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ordered his Diſciples to do for the ſurpaſſing the juſtice of the Scribes, and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> that they might enter into the Kingdom of Heaven. The Pre-judgments of Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made the Diſciples of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſtill doubt after his Reſurrection, if it was he who ſhould redeem <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to free them out of that pernicious doubt, reproaches them with their hardneſs of heart, and ſlowneſs to believe all that the Prophets have ſaid. And to diſengage them entirely from that falſe Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which ran amongſt the People, as <hi>Theophylact</hi> does remark in his Commentary upon the 24 Chap. of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> beginning with <hi>Moſes,</hi> and continuing through all the Prophets, he explains to them all that had been ſaid of him in all the Scriptures, as St. <hi>Luke</hi> does relate it in the laſt Chapter of his Goſpel. <hi>Christ</hi> does never refer People to Traditions for their Inſtruction in truths neceſſary to Salvation, but alwayes to the Scripture. <hi>If you believed Moſes,</hi> ſaid he to the <hi>Jews</hi> in St. <hi>John.</hi> Chap. 6. <hi>You would believe me alſo, becauſe it is of me he has writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; but if you believe not what he has written, how ſhould you believe what I tell you?</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays expreſly in his 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> Chap. 3. <hi>That the Holy Scriptures are able to make us wiſe unto Salvation through Faith which is in Jeſus Christ.</hi> And to explain this thought more amply he adds, <hi>All Scripture is given by Inſpiration of God, and is profitable for Doctrine, for Reproof, for Correction, for Inſtruction in Righteouſneſs, that the man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed unto all good Works.</hi> This is what the Fathers of the Council of <hi>Francfort</hi> expreſs in theſe terms, in the Capitulary of <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> lib. 2. cap. 30. <hi>Eſt plane Divina Scriptura Verax, est fixa, eſt caſta, eſt Caeleſtis Magisterii Instrumentum, &amp; Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terna
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51756:5"/>praedicatio puriſſimo nitens eloquio, est Lux mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talium, dicente Propheta, Lucerna pedibus meis verbum tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Domine, et Lumen Semitis meis. Eſt Vivax et mori ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciens, dicente Apostolo, Vivus eſt Sermo Dei &amp; efficax, &amp; penetrabilior omni gladio ancipiti, &amp; pertingens uſque ad diviſionem animae, ac Spiritus. Eſt tenebrarum diſcuſſio, Salomone teſtante, qui ait, Lucerna eſt mandatum legis &amp; lux vitae, &amp; increpatio, &amp; Diſciplina: de quo per Eſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am dicitur, De nocte ſpiritus meus vigilat ad te Deus, quia lux praecepta tua ſunt ſuper terram. The Holy Scripture is plainly true, is ſtable, is chaste, the Inſtrument of Celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Power, and an eternal Preaching ſhining throughout with a most pure eloquence, is the Light of Mortals, according to the ſaying of the Prophet,</hi> Thy Word, O Lord, is a Lamp to my feet, and a Light unto my pathes; <hi>Is quick and immortal, as the Apoſtle ſays,</hi> The Word of God is quick and Powerful, ſharper then a two-edged Sword, and piercing even to the dividing aſunder of Soul &amp; Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. <hi>Is the diſſipating &amp; diſpelling of thick darkneſs, witneſs</hi> Solomon, <hi>who ſays,</hi> The Commandment is a Lamp, and the Law is light, and reproofs of inſtruction are the way of life:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Es.</hi> 26. <hi>v.</hi> 9. <hi>in Edit.</hi> lxx.</note> 
               <hi>Of whom it is ſaid by</hi> Eſaiah, Every night my Spirit waiteth upon thee O God, becauſe thy Precepts are a light upon the earth. And as the Holy Writ poſſeſſes theſe advantages, not by reaſon of the words, but by reaſon of the truths which it contains, according to the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of St. <hi>Jerome</hi> in <hi>Cap.</hi> 1 <hi>ad Gal. Nec putemus in verbis Scripturarum eſſe Evangelium, ſed in ſenſu, non in ſuperficie, ſed in medulla, non in ſermonum foliis, ſed in radice ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis: Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles had reaſon in their Citations to apply themſelves more to the real ſence then to the meer words of the Holy VVrit. Moreover to inſtruct us, That all that has paſſed under the Law of Nature and of <hi>Moſes</hi> was the figure and ſhadow of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51756:5"/>what was to paſs under the Goſpel, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles give us very often the allegorical ſence of the paſſages which they Cite out of the Old Teſtament.</p>
            <p>The ſecond reaſon of Father <hi>Simon,</hi> which he calls <hi>a very evident proof,</hi> to ſhow that the Scripture is not ſufficient to decide Controverſies in matter of Religion, is taken from that the <hi>Socinions</hi> do agree with the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> that the only and true Principle of Religion is the Holy Writ, and that nevertheleſs they draw from thence very different Concluſions. If Father <hi>Simon</hi> ſaid, the <hi>Socinians</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants</hi> differ in the Concluſions, which they draw from the Scriptures, therefore one or other of 'em is in the errour, becauſe they do not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Scriptures aright, the argumentation would be pure; But I do not ſee by what <hi>Logick</hi> he draws this inference that the Scripture is not ſufficient to decide Controverſies; <hi>Since it is manifest that the</hi> Socinians <hi>govern themſelves by prejudgments in the explication of the Scripture,</hi> as Father <hi>Simon</hi> ſpeaks in his <hi>Critical Hiſtory of the Old Teſtament,</hi> Book 3 chap. 16. Therefore if the <hi>Socinians</hi> draw quite contrary Concluſions to what the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> do from the ſame Scriptures, it is not the obſcurity of the Scripture that is the cauſe thereof, but the prejudgments of the <hi>Socinians,</hi> which make 'em abuſe the Scripture to favour the Syſteme of Religion which they have invented independantly of Scripture. The Devil abuſes the Scripture to Tempt <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> and <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> reſiſts him by uſing the Scripture aright, <hi>Falſas de Scripturis Diaboli ſagitas veris Scripturarum frangit Clypeis,</hi> ſays <hi>St. Jerome:</hi> And this the <hi>Protestants</hi> do every day in their Controverſy with the <hi>Socintans;</hi> and this is what ought generally to be done in all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies upon matters of Religion; and if the Fathers of the firſt Ages be Cited in theſe Diſputes, it ought
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51756:6"/>only to make people ſenſible that thoſe perſons who ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyed the Scriptures to learn therein what it is God would have us believe and do to be ſaved, did draw the ſame Doctrine from thence, which we do who are alſo <hi>Orthodox,</hi> when they had no vail nor blind before their eyes, which hindred them from ſeeing the day and the light of the Word of God in the Scriptures, that is to ſay, when they had no Syſteme of Religion indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant of Scriptures. The <hi>Phariſees</hi> falſely concluded from that the Scripture ſays, <hi>That a man may leave his Wife by giving her a Writing, by which he declares that he puts her away,</hi> that a man was allowed to put away his Wife for any cauſe ſoever; but <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces them of an errour, not by tradition, but by the Scripture, as we read in the 19. chap. of <hi>St. Mathew.</hi> The <hi>Saducees</hi> who rejected all traditions, pretended to conclude from the Scripture that there would be no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Dead, and <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> did not tell them that they fell into that errour becauſe they did not joyn tradition to the Scripture, or becauſe they rejected all tradition, but he reſutes them by a concluſion drawn out of Scriptures, &amp; tells them, <hi>You are in an errour becauſe you do not underſtand the Scriptures; Erratis neſcientes Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turas.</hi> And indeed <hi>St. Auguſtine</hi> very judiciouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks, That the <hi>Hereticks</hi> are only ſo by their obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately perſevering to give a falſe ſence to the Scriptures which they do not underſtand, <hi>Omnes Haeretici Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras Catholicas legunt nec ob aliud ſunt Haeretici niſi quod eas non recte intelligentes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 7 <hi>de Gen. ad lit. cap.</hi> 9.</note> ſuas falſas Opiniones contra ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum veritatem pervicaciter aſſerunt.</hi> The ſame Holy Doctor in his 18th. Treatiſe upon the Goſpel of St. <hi>John:</hi> ſays, <hi>Non natae ſunt Haereſes &amp; quaedam Dogmata perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitatis illaqueantia animos, &amp; in profundum precipitantia, niſi cum Scripturae bonae intelliguntur non bene, &amp; quod in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51756:6"/>cis non bene intelligitur, etiam temere &amp; audacter aſſeritur. Hereſy and certain perverſe Tenets enſnaring peoples minds, and plunging them into the abyſs, have onely proceeded from a miſunderſtanding of the Scriptures, and when what is not well underſtood in them, is nevertheleſs raſhly and audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly aſſerted. Chromatius</hi> whom St. <hi>Jerome</hi> calls the moſt holy, moſt learned Biſhop of his time, tells us upon the 15 verſe of the 5. chap. of St. <hi>Mat.</hi> That the Scripture is clear, but that the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Hereticks</hi> endeavour to hide from us its perſpicuity by their perverſe interpretations; <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuam lucem praedicationis divinae pravis interpretationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus obtegere &amp; occultare nituntur, pro fide perfidiam praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cando &amp; lumen veritatis erroris tenebris obvelando.</hi> From all this it may be concluded, that when people diſpute againſt the <hi>Socinians</hi> and other Hereticks, to convert them, the method of <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> muſt be followed, and they muſt be Convicted of errour by the Scripture it ſelf. All that is not formally read in Scripture, or is not drawn from thence by an evident Concluſion, is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to errour, and by conſequence cannot be the Rule of our belief. The very Diſciples of <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> were miſtaken in the rumour which ran amongſt them that St. <hi>John</hi> did not dye, becauſe that rumour was onely grounded upon a concluſion falſely inferred from what <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> had ſaid to St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking of St <hi>John? If I will that he ſtay until I come, what's that to thee.</hi> Nay the Scripture ſeems to ſhow us this on purpoſe that we might learn, that what in matter of Religion is not well grounded upon its authority, is not worthy of faith: <hi>Sine authoritate Scripturarum garrulitas non habet fidem.</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Jerome.</hi> All the Fathers of the firſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges teach us this truth in all the diſputes they had with the Hereticks of their time. For, as <hi>Janſenius</hi> that learned Prelate of <hi>Ipre</hi> does obſerve in his Book In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51756:7"/>
               <hi>Augustinus,</hi> they ſo formed their ſentiments by the Holy Scriptures,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>lib, Broem. C.</hi> 5.</note> that they almoſt expreſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the ſame form: <hi>In antiquis patribus</hi> ſaith he, <hi>eorumque diſputationibus duo ſunt conſideranda magno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere; primum quod ex principiis verbi Dei ſenſus ſuos, &amp; fere verba promerent; ſecuntium quod religioſe intra terminos oppugnatae ab errore veritatis ſine ulla ſuperfluarum multo minus curioſarum, frivolarum, atque inutilium quaestie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num intermixtione remanerent. In the ancient Fathers and their diſputes two things are principally to be conſidered. Firſt that they draw their ſence and tenets, nay and almoſt their very terms out of the Principles of the Word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, that they religiouſly remain within the bounds of the Truth that was combated by Errour without any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termixtion of ſuperfluous, much leſs of curious, frivolous and impertinent queſtions.</hi> Thus as Scripture is the onely way to decide queſtions of Religion, <hi>panormitanus</hi> had reaſon to ſay that people ought rather to believe a Lay-man who authorizes himſelf by Scripture, then a Pope and a whole Council, when they act without its authority. <hi>Magis credendum laico ſi ſcriptur as adferat, quam Papae &amp; toti Concilio ſi abſque ſcripturis agant.</hi> St. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> who has given a Catalogue of all the Hereſies which had been until his time, and remarks the abuſe which the Authors of thoſe Hereſies have made of the Holy Writ to eſtabliſh their Errours, does not attribute this to the obſcurity of the Scripture, but to the Hereticks not having applyed themſelves to Scripture with a Spirit of Piety; for it is a conſtant Principle, ſays that Saint, that all the ſaving Truths are found clearly in the Scripture by thoſe who read them with judgment and a ſpirit with piety. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>St. Auguſtine</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:51756:7"/>diſputing againſt <hi>Maximin,</hi> an <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhop, lays down for Principle that the Authority alone of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture is to be inſiſted upon: <hi>Non ego Nicaenum Concilium tibi, nectu mihi Ariminenſet amquam praejudicatur us profer as: nec ego hujus authoritate, nec tu illius detineris. Scripturarum authoritatibus non quorumlibet propriis, ſed utriſque com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munibus teſtibus, res cam re, ratio cum ratione decertet. I do not urge to thee the Nicene Council nor do thou to me that of Ariminum as a forejudging of the Controverſie: Neither do I mean the authority of the one, neither art thou bound by that of the other. But let matter of fact &amp; the reaſon of each Council be tryed by authority of the Scriptures, which both are bound to admit as witneſſing the Divine Truths.</hi> He ſays in the ſame place, that the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> inſiſted only upon Scriptures. And indeed it would be impertinent to place the Bible in the midſt of the Councils, unleſs it were to put them in mind, that their Deciſions would not be worthy of faith, unleſs they were founded upon the authority of the Scripture. Which has been admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably well ſaid by <hi>Optat</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Mileve</hi> in his Book againſt <hi>Parmenian; Quaerendi ſunt judices—in terris de hac re nullum poterit reperiri judicium, de Caelo quaerendus eſt judex. Sed ut quid pulſamus ad Coelum, cum habeamus hic in Evangelio Testamentum? Terrenus Pater cum ſe in Confinio ſenſerit mortis, timens ne poſt mortem ſuam rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta pace litigent fratres, adhibitis teſtibus voluntatem ſuam de pectore morituro transfert in tabulas diu duraturas. Et ſi fuerit inter fratres contentio nata, non itur ad tumulum ſed quaeritur Teſtamentum. Judges muſt be ſought in the caſe—No judgment can be had in this matter upon earth, a Judge is to be ſought for from Heaven. But why ſhould we have recourſe to Heaven, ſeeing we have here its will in the Goſpel? An Earthly Father when he ſees himſelf upon the brim of Death, fearing least after his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51756:8"/>death, the peace coming to be broken, the Brethren ſhould be at variance, having called the witneſſes tranſmitteth his Will from his dying breath into Deeds of long continuance. And if any contention ſhall ariſe amongſt the Brethren, let them not go to the Tomb, but ſeek out the Teſtament.</hi> In ſhort, even as the Goſpel does aſſure us, that thoſe who having <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets do not live conformably to their Doctrine, would not be Converted by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations of the Dead though they ſhould return, ſo thoſe who are not inſtructed and perſwaded of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving truths by the Holy Scripture, will never be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by tradition. Father <hi>Simon</hi> cannot diſpute this in the leaſt, ſince he ſays himſelf in the 10. Chap. of the 1. Book of his <hi>Critical Hiſt. That it often happens that men being the Keepers of Tradition, do blend therein what they have invented, and then it is a hard matter to distinguiſh the true Traditions from thoſe which are falſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third proof which I find in the Critical Hiſt. of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Simon</hi> to ſhow the inſufficiency of the Scripture to decide Controverſies in matter of Religion, is <hi>That there has been in all times in the Churches an abridgment of Religion independantly of Scripture.</hi> Nay he pretends that it is upon the account of that abridgment, that the Fathers have explained the Scriptures, and that the Councils have decided the Controverſies of their time. I do not doubt but that in all ages there have Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſms been made for the inſtruction of Children and the ſhalloweſt Capacities; or abridgments of Religion; But I deny that thoſe abridgments were made indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly of Scripture. I maintain againſt Father <hi>Simon</hi> that thoſe who govern'd the Church took care to collect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an abridgment the cleareſt ſentences of Scripture, and the moſt neceſſary to inſtruct the faithful in the ſaving. Truths, and the Fathers and Councils had reaſon after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51756:8"/>to decide the Controverſies according to thoſe abridgments, ſince their taking that Courſe was to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain obſcure paſſages by thoſe which are clearer, as good ſence doth require. All the paſſages which I have already Cited, do manifeſtly prove what I urge; nay and if we may believe thoſe Authors who have treated of Eccleſiaſtical Offices, the leſſons of the Scripture, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſtill reads at this day on <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Whitſon-eve,</hi> are onely the Catechiſms and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions which were given to the <hi>Catechumenes,</hi> or Novice Proſelytes who were baptized on thoſe days. The moſt ancient abridgment of Religion which we have left of antiquity is the Symbol which is ſaid to have been compoſed by the Apoſtles; But this Abridgment is not independant of the Scripture, as St, <hi>Aug.</hi> ſays, book the firſt of the Symbol to the <hi>Catechumenes</hi> Chap. 1. <hi>Iſta verba quae audiſt is, per divin as Scriptur as ſparſa ſunt, ſed inde collecta, &amp; ad unum redacta ne tardorum hominum me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moria laboraret, ut omnis homo poſſit dicere, poſſit tenere quod credit. Thoſe words you have heard are ſcattered thro the Holy Scriptures, but Collected from thence, and reduced in a Body that they might not be burdenſome to the Memories of ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Capacities, and that every man might ſay and remember what he believes.</hi> And <hi>Rabanus Maurus</hi> ſpeaking of the ſame Symbole in the 56th Chapter of his ſecond Book <hi>de Inſtitutione Clericorum,</hi> ſays, <hi>In quo quidem pauca ſunt Verba, ſed omnia continentur Sacramenta, de totis enim Scripturis haec breviatim Collecta ſunt ab Apostolis, ut quoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am plures Credentium Litter as neſciunt, vel qui ſciunt, prae occupatione ſeculi legere non poſſunt, haec corde retinentes, habeant ſufficientem ſibi ſcientiam ſalutarem. In which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are contained but few Words, but all the Mysteries be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus briefly collected from all the Scriptures, by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, that ſeveral of the Believers who know not how to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51756:9"/>read, or thoſe who do, being hindred from reading by the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the world, getting theſe by heart, might have a Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſufficient to work out their Salvation.</hi> The Church of <hi>England</hi> ſpeaking of this Abridgment, as well as of thoſe which are called the Symboles of <hi>Nice</hi> and of St. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> ſays in the Synods of <hi>London</hi> in 1552. 1562. <hi>The three Creeds, Nicene Creed,</hi> Athanaſius's <hi>Creed. &amp; that which is commouly cal'd</hi> Apoſtles <hi>Creed, ought thro'ly to be receibed: for they may be proved by moſt certain Warrants of Holy Scripture.</hi> St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> did certainly never own any Abridgement of Religion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependently of Scripture, ſince in his Epiſtle to <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peius</hi> he demands that they ſhould ſhow him in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that Hereticks were not to be baptized again, to perſwade him that it is an Apoſtolical Tradition. <hi>Si aut in Evangelio Praecipitur, aut in Apoſtolorum epistolis, aut Actibus continetur, ut a quacumque haereſi venientes non baptizentur, ſed tantum manus illis imponantur in Poenitentiam, obſervetur divina haec &amp; ſancta Traditio.</hi> If there can be ſhown any Precept of the Goſpel, or in the Epiſtles, or Acts of the Apoſtles, that thoſe who are converted from what Hereſy ſoever, ought not to be baptized, but only to be reconcil'd to the Church by Repentance, let that Divine and Holy Tradition be obſerved. This Abridgement was unknown to <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> who ſays in his diſpute againſt <hi>Hermogenes,</hi> Chap. 22. <hi>Adoro Scripturae plenitudinem. — Scriptum eſſe doceat Hermogenis officina, ſi non eſt Scriptum, timeat illud Vae adjicientibus aut detrahentibus deſtinatum.</hi> 
               <q>I adore the fulneſs of Scripture; let <hi>Hermogenes</hi> demonſtrate that it is Written;</q> 
               <hi>If it be not writen, let him fear that Woe which is pronounced againſt thoſe who add or leſſen it.</hi> The ſame in his Book of the Fleſh of <hi>Chriſt</hi> Chap. 7. diſputing againſt <hi>Apelles,</hi> he has not recourſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51756:9"/>to the Pretended Abridgements of Father <hi>Simon,</hi> but he tells that Hereſiarque, <hi>Non Recipio quod extra Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam de tuo infers; I do not allow of what thou urgeſt that is not in Scripture.</hi> This Abridgement was unknown to St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> who in his Book of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church,</hi> againſt the Epiſtle of <hi>Petitian,</hi> Chap. 11. <hi>ſays, Quis quis aliud Evangelizaverit, Anathema ſit, Whoſoever preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ought elſe for Goſpel, let him be accurſed,</hi> and Chap. 12. <hi>Aut legat mihi hoc in Scripturis, &amp; non ſit Anathema; Or let him produce me this in Scriptures, and he ſhall not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed.</hi> And in the ſame Chapter, <hi>Si autem non ea de ſacris Scripturis legunt, ſed ſuis contentionibus perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere conantur, Credo illa quae in Scripturis ſanctis leguntur, non Credo iſta quae ab Haereticis vanis dicuntur. But if they do not read thoſe things in the Holy Scriptures, but endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to perſwade by their Wranglings, I believe thoſe things which are read in Scriptures, I do not believe thoſe which are aſſerted by vain Hereticks.</hi> The ſame Doctor in the 2d. Book <hi>de Nup. &amp; Concup.</hi> Chap. 33. ſays, <hi>Iſta Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſia judicem quaerit, judicet ergo Chriſtus, &amp; cui rei mors ejus profuerit, ipſe dicat — judicet cum illo &amp; Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, quia in Apoſtolo ipſe loquitur Chriſtus. This Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy requires a Judge, therefore let Christ judge, and ſay of what Advantage his Death hath been, and let the Apoſtle judge with him, becauſe Chriſt himſelf ſpeaks in the Apoſtle.</hi> In his Book of Grace, and free will Chap. 13. <hi>Sedeat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nos judex Apostolus Joannes, Let the Apoſtle John judge between us.</hi> And in the 2d. Book againſt <hi>Creſconius,</hi> Chap. 32. <hi>Litter as Cypriani non ut Canonicas habeo, ſed eas ex Canonicis conſidero, &amp; quod in eis divinarum Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum autoritati congruit, cum laude ejus accipio; quod autem non congruit, cum pace ejus reſpuo. I do not allow of the Letters of Cyprian as Canonical, but I judge of them by the canonical Scriptures, and what in them is congruous to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51756:10"/>the Authority of the Holy Scriptures, I receive with due praiſe to him; but what is incongruous,</hi> I <hi>Reject with his leave.</hi> In ſhort, this Abridgement was unknown to the Councils, ſeeing they placed the Scriptures in the midſt of them, to ſerve for a Rule to their Deciſions, which would have been to no purpoſe if there had been in all times in the Church an Abridgement of Religion independant of the Scriptures. Father <hi>Simons</hi> ſaying, That the Apoſtles preached the Goſpel before they wrote it, and that in the time of St. <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> there were ſtill ſeveral Churches who believed in the Goſpel by Tradition, without having ſeen it in Writing, ſerves little to Authorize his pretended Abridgement, for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is that when we ſay, that the Scriptures contain clearly all that is neceſſary to Salvation, we do not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Truths couched upon Paper in the Scripture, againſt the ſame truths uttered by the tongue of the Preachers; we know that the Prophets and Apoſtles ought to have been believed when they preached the Truths which the Holy Ghoſt inſpired into them, as well as when they reduced 'em into Writing; But we only ſay that the Apoſtles and Prophets have reduced the ſame truths which they Preached into Writing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch a manner, that for the Regulating of our Faith we only need to have recourſe to their Writing. This is what St. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſays, in his third Book againſt Hereſies, Chap. 1. <hi>Non enim per alios diſpoſitionem ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutis nostrae cognovimus, quam per eos, per quos evangelium pervenit ad nos, quod quidem tunc praeconiaverunt; postea vero per Dei voluntatem in Scripturis nobis tradiderunt, fundamentum &amp; columnam fidei noſtrae futurum. We know not by others the Diſpoſition of our Salvation, than
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51756:10"/>by thoſe from whom the Goſpel came to us, which indeed, they then Preached: But afterwards by the will of God they delivered to us in Scriptures, to be the Foundation and Pillar of our Faith.</hi> If Father <hi>Simon</hi> asks us what aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance we can have that the ſaving truths were not alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Holy Writ, we can anſwer him that the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition or Preaching of the Goſpel in all Ages, was the inſtrument which God made uſe of, to make known to us that the Scripture is the Word of God, and that it was never altered after ſuch a manner, but that it ſtill contains very clearly what we ought to believe, and what we ought to do to be ſaved.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fides ex audi tu Rom.</hi> 10.17.</note> But that it is God who hath perſwaded us inwardly of the Truth of this Preaching; and this anſwer is very true, ſince that the Faith is a gift from God, and very conformable to what <hi>St. Auguſtine</hi> ſayes, ſpeaking to God in the 5. chap. of his 6th. Book of his Confeſſions. <hi>Perſuaſiſti mihi, non qui crederent libris tuis, ſed qui non crederent, eſſe cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pandos: Nec audiendos eſſe ſi qui forte dicerent, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde ſcis illos unius veri &amp; veraciſſimi Dei Spiritu eſſe humano ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neri miniſtratos.</hi> 
               <q>Thou haſt perſwaded me, that thoſe who do not believe in thy Books, not thoſe who do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, are guilty; nor are they to be given Ear to, if they ſhould by chance ſay, Whence knoweſt thou that they were adminiſtred to Humane Kind in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the moſt true and upright God.</q> I have nothing more <hi>Sir,</hi> then to make an end with beſeeching you to thank God for me, that he has given me by his mercy that precious gift of the faith, and perſwaded me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Idolatry, <hi>Heterodox</hi> Traditions, &amp; Superſtitious Noveities of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; to embrace an <hi>Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox</hi> Communion, which profeſſes to love the Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, fear God, and honour the King, and to Rule her Morels as well as her worſhip and Faith onely by the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51756:11"/>Scripture divinely inſpired, <hi>non taliter fecit omni Nationi,</hi> and to deſire the ſame God to continue to me his Grace, and Protection, whom I heartily pray that he would more and more ſhed abroad his Bleſſings over your worthy Perſon, and over the Lady <hi>Katherine</hi> Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counteſs <hi>Ranelaugh,</hi> Your moſt Accompliſhed, Godly, Charitable and Bountiful Siſter, and over all your No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Family.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt Humble and moſt Obedient Servant, <hi>C. M. Du Veil.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
